Finding Aid for Jens C. Zorn papers, 1956-1995
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Jens C. Zorn papers 1956-1995
Zorn, Jens C., 1931-
1 linear foot
0389 Aa 2
Jens Zorn was a professor of physics and administrator at the University of Michigan. This collection represents his teaching and work in the field of physics, including some of his research and active participation in the International Conference of Atomic Physics. Zorn’s papers also document his many roles in the university community, including activities in the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts; the University of Michigan Press; and the University Council.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Professor Zorn (donor no. 8310 ) in 1994.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Jens Zorn was born on June 19, 1931 and grew up in Los Angeles, California and Bloomington, Indiana. He earned his A.B. degree at Miami University in 1955 and a Ph.D. in physics at Yale University in 1961. He came to the University of Michigan in 1962 as an assistant professor of physics, and became full professor in 1970. Experimental atomic physics and laboratory astrophysics were some of his primary research areas, among several others. In addition to teaching and research duties, Zorn served in many administrative capacities, including participating on committees for instrument shop supervision, graduate curriculum review, and graduate student fellowships. From 1988 to 1991, he was co-chair of the International Conference on Atomic Physics.
Zorn was very active in the university as a whole. Several of his major assignments are documented in the collection. From 1967 to 1976, he taught a freshman seminar at the Residential College on the effect of technology on Appalachian life. He has also served many administrative functions at the college. From 1977 to 1982, he served on the executive committee of the University of Michigan Press, and he was the chair of the Curriculum Committee for the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts (LS&A), between 1980 and 1982. From 1988 to 1990, he served as chair of University Council; during his service, the council dealt with the issues of free speech and the harassment of protesters.
In addition to these major assignments, Zorn worked on a number of committees, including the committee to consider granting tenure to part-time professors; a review of the ROTC curriculum; organizing a grass-roots effort in 1975 to gain permanent status as dean for then temporary LSA dean Billy Frye; and leading an effort to improve the language proficiency of foreign teaching assistants during the early 1980s. Zorn was also involved in LS&A grievance committees dealing with personnel disputes and tenure denials.
The Jens Zorn Papers document his professional and academic activities. The collection has been divided into three series: Biographical Material, Physics, and University Activities.
Subjects:
International Conference on Atomic Physics.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Physics.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Zorn, Jens C.
- Biographical Material
  The Biographical Material series, 1980-1995 (0.2 linear ft.) consists of a single folder which includes a vita written in September 1994, a statement written in 1980 describing his contributions to the university, and a print-out of an e-mail describing his role in a number of his university activities.
  - Miscellaneous, 1980-1995 (Box 1)
- Physics Material
  Physics, 1956-1991 (0.5 linear ft.) is divided into three subseries, arranged alphabetically: Administrative - Miscellaneous Memos & Reports, 1990, International Conference of Atomic Physics (ICAP), and Research. The primary item contained in the ICAP file is a script titled, "Informal discussion of the history of ICAP." The Research subseries primarily consists of grant proposals, which document the planning, progress, staffing and funding of research projects. Some files also contain initial drafts, final reports and published articles. Four projects are filed individually and listed by title. A fifth file contains miscellaneous research projects that are lacking a more complete documented record. The sixth file is a bound booklet containing Zorn's research projects completed when he was a graduate student at Yale.
  - Administrative -- Miscellaneous Memos & Reports, 1964-1971 (Box 1)
  - International Conference on Atomic Physics, 1988-1991 (Box 1)
  - Research
    - "Gas Molecular Solid State Interaction Studies," 1966-1969 (Box 1)
    - Grant and Research Proposals, 1966-1979 (Box 1)
    - "Measurement of N2 Velocity Distributions in the Upper Atmosphere," 1968-1967 (Box 1)
    - "Non Destructive Examination of Surface by Neutral Atom Probes," 1967-1970 (Box 1)
    - "Time of Flight Experiments with Metastable Atoms and Molecules," 1973-1975 (Box 1)
    - US-Mexico Cooperative Science Program/"Time Flight Spectroscopy," 1973-1976 (Box 1)
    - Yale Research, 1956-1959 (Box 1)
- University Activities
  University Activities, 1967-1993 (0.3 linear ft.) consists of 10 subseries, ranging from one to three folders each. Each subseries documents the activities described in the biography. They consist primarily of memos and reports except for the University of Michigan Press Executive Committee which consists primarily of manuscript reviews written by Zorn. A number of files contain campus newspaper clippings relating to the issues and events documented in the folder.
  - Appointment of Billy Frye as LS&A Dean, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Curriculum Committee, 1982-1983 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee Correspondence
    - Department of Anthropology, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Department of Communications, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Language Proficiency of Foreign Teaching Assistants, 1982-1983
    - Personnel Issues, 1982-1983 (Box 1)
  - Part time Tenure Policy, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Residential College
    - Director Search Committee, 1976-1977 (Box 1)
    - Freshman Seminar-"The effect of Technology in Appalachia," 1967-1974 (Box 1)
    - Memos & Reports, 1968-1974 (Box 1)
  - ROTC Review, 1974-1975. (Box 1)
  - University Of Michigan Press Executive Committee, 1980-1981 (Box 1)
  - University Council
    - Background Info/Meeting Notes/Memos-in Workbook Format, 1980-1981 (Box 1)
    - Memos/Meeting Notes/Reports, 1988-1989 (Box 1)
    - Memos and Reports, undated (Box 1)